[Music]
the following is the production of
Frankie Freitas and the internet resume
of holography
hello this is Frankie Freitas and
welcome to hollow talk the internet
laser and holography talk show our
toll-free number is
[Music]
1-800-458-3525 or you can send an email
to holotalk
holoworld.com we've got telephone calls
we've got emails we've got special
guests coming up so thank you for tuning
in and let's get this week's show on the
road
hello this is Frankie Freitas and
welcome to another week of hello talk
Our Guest this week is Brian Monahan
from Pennsylvania Pulp and Paper located
in Glenside Pennsylvania they have a
website at
www.holoprism.com that's
h-o-l-o-p-r-i-s-m
M
www.holoprism.com now as you're
listening to the show you can go over
and visit their website we also have a
link on a whole talk page you can just
click on the link and the show will
continue to play with the real audio
player in the background as you visit
the website our musical guest this week
is a band called Brazil 2000.
now Brian has a very interesting company
they're producing Holograms using
desktop computers and holographic
printers now they're not doing the
traditional three-dimensional Holograms
they're doing what we refer to as 2D 3D
Holograms which means it has almost a
spectral quality to it and it does have
some depth but the depth is more in
layers than anything else
they use the desktop computers to both
design the images themselves and also
bring images in that are supplied to
them on disks
and also as Brian tells us in the
interview more and more commonly through
the internet so so it's going to be a
very interesting interview before we get
to that interview I just want to point
out one thing there's going to be a
major laser and holography exhibit
in this area now if you live in the New
York
Philadelphia Baltimore Washington D.C
Corridor or anywhere in that area all
the way west to say Harrisburg this
exhibit is going to be right in your
area now at this point in time there
have not been any press releases sent
out on this so I cannot comment on when
the exhibit's going to be or where it's
going to be located but I will let you
do this I'm going to give you an email
address that email address is as follows
exhibit at holoworld.com that email
address is exhibit holoworld.com if you
send an email to that address I'm going
to put up a special folder for you
and I'm going to put all the emails into
that folder and as soon as the
information is released
and I get the go ahead on releasing some
of that information I will make sure
that you are the first people to know
about it I'm also going to look into
perhaps having Hollow talk listeners
receive maybe a discount or something in
that nature if you come out to see this
show it's going to be approaching
holography and lasers through science
and technology so it's going to be
something to see
now this isn't going to be a long show
and I've moved the studio the studio
equipment and everything we need to
broadcast is now over at the Discovery
Center of Science and Technology we're
going to be doing this show live in
front of people uh each weekend so we
may have to change the date that it goes
up we'll have to see about that but in
any case we're going to make this a
short show because some of the equipment
is hooked up other parts of the
equipment is not hooked up so we're just
going to go right into the Brian Monahan
interview and let's see what Brian has
to say about his company Pennsylvania
Pulp and Paper and what they're doing
with desktop holography
good morning hi Brian how you doing not
bad not bad
um we're talking with Brian Monahan from
Pennsylvania Pulp and Paper
and they're located
in Glenside Pennsylvania Brian how you
doing today not bad Frank can you okay
uh to tell you the truth when I was
looking through your materials last
night and well we've known each other
for a while anyway but to be honest with
you we could probably do two shows on
what it is that you guys
could you tell us a little bit about
some of the hotter things that are going
on down there yeah uh well just recently
as a matter of fact uh the past two days
we have uh done some really amazing
breakthroughs in the realm of photos
basically we are doing a new process
which will enable us to
make
dot matrix type hologram at a extremely
extremely high speeds in very large
formats and also in cylindrical formats
oh interesting yeah the the big thing
about that is our industry which is uh
in the boss holography industry theme
line where shim meet up on an embossing
cylinder are
taboo
especially with our cross grading a
rainbow cross grading so we've developed
a technique to be able to
write our holography directly into a
cylinder and produce a fairly
long-lasting cylinder with absolutely no
seam lines well that's incredible yeah
it's pretty interesting now what size
can you go up to with this you said
large format what do you mean large
format well right now we are set up to
do 30 inches by 40 inches
at extremely high speed wow uh we are in
the works of the engineering a plan to
do a 110 inch wide cylinders well and
mainly for some larger wide web unboxers
in the country
it is absolutely fantastic and you know
the best thing is I look back at when I
met you and we worked uh took your class
with the bikini lasers and my biggest
goal in life was to be able to get a 10
milliliti and setting up endless hours
of
tables and carpets and and cement in my
basement and coming out with what you
might call a hologram on several
occasions he really spurred me and now I
look back look back at that and look
where we are now with uh you know
absolutely four dot matrix Labs we have
owned clean rooms for Coating
photoresist
electroforming in Boston and a lot of a
lot of very high-powered and fun lasers
to play with
now the holography part of your business
for Pennsylvania Pulp and Paper that's
running what percentage would you say
that is of your business today about 95
95 it's incredible yeah now you do what
they call desktop holography
would that be a correct term for it uh
if you're working on desktop computers
and yeah design stage yeah that would be
a good time uh everything that we do is
uh electronic
um we did not use any masks or any uh
anything like that maybe with a
conventional 2D 3D holography or models
so someone scans an image in to your
computer or you receive that on a disk
if they wanted something reproduced yes
or both a lot right now is coming uh via
the Internet oh no kidding yeah as JPEG
images or whatever uh bitmap but not
yeah yeah and what we do is we have a
our computer system will break down a
bitmap image just as a BMP file may have
256 different colors
uh our computer will interpret it and
our machine will run at 256 different
angles I see so the picture has all the
colors to make the picture we shoot a
hologram with all the angles to make the
same picture pixel by pixel now you had
a couple interesting projects and one of
the ones that goes back a little ways
Star Trek generations yeah and then
you've got the Men in Black video covers
uh video cassette cover as well yeah
tell us a little about that
actually the Star Trek one was the good
that you know we won uh we won a few
Awards with the ihma the international
hologram manufacturer Association for
the Star Trek box he he and it really in
my opinion turned out
turned out really pretty fantastic it
achieved its goal
um the that led into a lot of other
projects some smaller ones uh but then
eventually into the Men in Black which
uh last year uh definitely if not to
date was the largest holographic
packaging job in the world I was looking
through your materials last night 1 30
in the morning in bed
just to get ready for doing the show
today and I picked out this one piece
here which is premium mirror board one
yeah and I thought to myself I wonder if
this could be used as a regular mirror
so I went down into the lab because I
had my lab at my house
and believe it or not it does a nice job
reflecting laser light you can take away
you could cut this up and make front
surface mirrors I'm almost positive that
the surface on this is so good that I
could use it in the holographic setup
and make a hologram with it well we got
a new end youth now for it on cardboard
but you know what we had no idea what it
would be used for when we introduced
that product it took us about a year and
a half to be able to design it that it
would uh be printable and you could cut
it into a box and fold it and glue it
and but it still had to have that
absolutely perfect mirror condition and
it took a while once we made it we
really didn't have too much of an idea
who would use it and how it would be
used sort of like the laser itself yeah
but uh it's amazing we have customers
using it for things as crazy as mirrors
or inmates in present no kidding uh that
they can't have anything sharp this they
get a piece of this mirror along with
their toothbrushes and then they can
shave in it
incredible yeah actually it's it's very
interesting I think I'm going to try
working with it a little bit it doesn't
work too well on the spread Bean you
know once the beans spread out but to
take the beam around the table this
works just as uh good as one of the
little front surface mirrors and they
have something there what are some of
the other things you've done a number of
different labels for uh
for uh breweries like middle or Genuine
Draft right well that one we weren't
involved with that one was a good uh
story to tell our customers
shot by chromogen I said several years
ago but the sales results from that were
pretty amazing so we we like to help the
sales results of that one uh but we've
been uh really pretty diverse it's a
really amazing where all the ends of our
holography is going uh from everything
from again the the packaging Arena which
is very hot right now we're trying to
push more into the publishing area for
uh these book covers annual report
covers uh things of that nature are our
large format uh holography or large
machine will you know when it produces
the 30 by 40 works really very well with
uh posters and point-of-purchase
displays things of that nature I you
know we're we're still a relatively
small company
and it's difficult when you try to get
into this industry uh thinking that you
can compete with the American banknotes
of the world
whether producing a billion little half
inch Holograms a year yeah
so we've kind of took a different
direction in the packaging in the large
format and we may not sell a billion of
our Holograms but if we sell a million
sheets uh that are 30 by 40 inches it's
a lot of square inches of holographic
material yeah I see your
your applications here on the Christmas
cards and
comic book covers I mean it's just on
everything
it's been it it has been actually the
best part of it it has been a lot of fun
doing it we work with a lot of good
customers uh m m Mars is a project we
got finished doing it took about six
months where we mastered uh I would say
13 14 different originations and combine
that into a seamless background pattern
to make uh a two foot by three foot
hologram
that would be embossed and then adhere
to the side of a candy cart for retail
distribution and it took a long time to
shoot that many originations and to get
it just right so we had a great customer
to work with and when we were all done
you look at it and it's fantastic is
that the one with candy or names on it
yeah you know I have that up I have that
hanging in the center here yeah you know
it's really a fantastic piece and uh
we're starting to see a lot more people
willing to venture into new and unique
things like that
and it really uh it's really fun you
know when somebody comes to us and says
we want to do this or you want to do
something unique uh we have a lot of fun
improving it and uh and showing them
what what capabilities that we have and
you know what can be done up there I
just want to let the listeners know that
Pennsylvania Pulp and Paper has a
website let me give you the web address
and there's also a link right on the
whole talk page it's
www.holoprism Dot com
www.holoprism.com and you can go to
their website even as you're listening
to this show because the real audio
player will continue to play in the
background as you surf the web so if
you'd like to find out more about
Pennsylvania Pulp and Paper just you can
go right now to their website and the
show will continue you can still listen
to the show while you're cruising around
the web there I think that guy I will
mention to you that where people
understand the internet well that the
our website is Antiquated and old uh and
it's we're in the works of updating it
and not making it so graphically
intensive and more user friendly but for
two and a half years old I did a job
yeah I'm sure it did you have a nice
CD-ROM too an instructional cd-run yeah
and that's that you know again that's
available to people uh who are
interested in holography
want to know a little bit more very
Basics on how Holograms are made with
boss holography and a little bit more
about what our company does
let me ask you this before we close out
here do you ever get any comments from
anybody that what you're doing is not
holography
does anybody ever say that yeah some
some people do some people uh what's
your response to that
well my response is what we're doing is
considered a two-dimensional holography
we're interfering two games of plays
that like to create a
an interference pattern
DNA interference pattern of complex is a
three-dimensional image would be or
two-dimensional image it really doesn't
matter and some of the work that we've
done in the past we've contract out to
get a three-dimensional image or
stereographic image and combine it and
integrate it with our uh holographic our
2D Prismatic and what the biggest thing
that our target audience is is normally
people that have products that are under
in-store lighting conditions where ours
works very well especially the dot
matrix it shows a lot of color and a lot
of movement and a three-dimensional
hologram it would be difficult to see
sometimes the combination of the two of
them are dot matrix philography gets
them in three-dimensional holography
Wows them yes so there's a place for
everything and I think eventually we'll
be getting into doing some Freedom 3D
origination
yeah stuff like that we we've been
working very hard on on protecting what
we're doing we just got issued a patent
last week on uh registering lithography
to holography
congratulations on that people said that
that's not true holography
same thing it's a unique product in
itself yeah I see moving in that
direction yeah I'm going to try and
describe this to you so you know what
I'm talking about there's a piece that
was in your package with two angels on
it
and they're looking up towards the
clouds and I I see you moving more
towards uh the Imaging the actual
Imaging itself with this piece because I
think this piece grabbed my attention
right away and then unfortunately you
don't have the trended piece but the
true uh printing the true lithography
would be printed in register to that
hologram to add some color and texture
so it's just not all silver and hologram
if you're listening to this show and
you're finding it hard to imagine
exactly what it is we're talking about
you may want to go over to the
Pennsylvania Pulp and Paper site
but chances are you've already had a
chance to see something that's been
produced by Pennsylvania Pulp and Paper
at the time you're over the video store
pick up the Men in Black video oh mine's
reading written in French I just noticed
that yeah we did uh so far about 16
countries including Russia and Saudi
Arabia no kidding we'll pick up the Men
in Black video cassette box and you'll
see exactly what it is that they're
doing over Pennsylvania Pulp and Paper
so Brian we're gonna head out right uh
this is the first show that I've done
live from the Discovery Center so you
were sort of a guinea pig this week
because this equipment just got hooked
up but I think everything worked out
okay yep if you don't try something new
you'll never get anywhere now you need a
little help getting that real audio
player to work right yep I'm going to
send an email to you to show you how you
can do that easily with America online
because it's a little bit different than
with a direct internet dial-up account
wonderful all right I appreciate it all
right thanks for being a guest thank you
Frank take care bye-bye
Brian Monahan interview uh we're going
to get the questions next week
and we had a bunch of questions coming
in in fact uh we had the best week we
ever had last week in fact on Monday uh
when Steve Benton interview first
started we had 100 no
1114 listeners on Monday
1049 listeners on Tuesday and I'm not
quite sure the number on Wednesday I
forgot it actually but it was over a
thousand So within three days we had 3
000 listeners Monday Tuesday and
Wednesday of the show we've got a bunch
of questions that came through we're
going to get to the questions next week
you know every other week we have a
special guest and then we get the
questions and other things on the excuse
me odd weeks so don't forget our
toll-free number
1-800-458-3525 or send an email to
holotalk hollowworld.com
if you want information about that
holography exhibit that's coming to this
area in New York Philly Baltimore
Washington DC area easy drive from any
of those places uh send an email to
exhibit holoworld.com and I'll fill you
in on that so thank you for tuning in to
whole talk and don't forget our special
musical guest this week is a band called
Brazil 2000 uh here for your listening
pleasure don't forget to tune in for
that and this is frankfurrias once again
for holotalk thank you for tuning in and
I'll see you next week